The immediate reaction might be that it
seems unnatural to consume a nutrient
that has no calories, but is so much
sweeter than sugar. And it just so
happens that a study indicates it does
have an effect on our brain. But is it
really something to worry over?
Non-nutritive sweeteners NNS like
aspartame, saccharine, sucralose and the
like are molecules that have a
particular chemical structure that does
not allow them to be metabolized to
generate cellular energy and therefore
they do not produce calories. However,
because of the distinct chemical
structure, they tend to be as sweet or
many many times sweeter than plain
sugar. In this case, we'll be focused on
sucralose, a component of multiple
popular foods and drinks from Splenda
packets to diet sodas to sugar-free
shakes and puddings and plenty more. In
this study, researchers fed the same
group of young men and women three
different drinks separated by at least
two weeks between the conditions. So,
one drink had just water, another was
sucrossse, sugar, and the final is
obviously sucralose, our non-nutritive
sweetener of interest. Then the
researchers performed a blood test and
did a series of brain scans as well as
measured hunger. Now the reason this
study is important is because many
people consume non-nutritive sweeteners
to avoid the calorie burden from certain
foods and drinks and to still somewhat
satisfy the feelings of sweetness that
one might want. However, animal studies
have shown that these caloriefree
sweeteners stimulate hunger by
interfering with the usual neural
responses to food consumption and even
sugar consumption. Specifically, the
region of the brain heavily implicated
in hunger. And there are specific blood
flow changes that occur that have a
relationship to feelings of hunger.
Specifically, sugar and likely other
foods reduce the activation of the
hypothalamus by reducing blood flow to
the region of the brain. that relates to
reduced hunger. So, let me quickly
clarify here that the researchers aren't
saying that sugar is a satiating
nutrient relative to other nutrients.
They're simply saying that compared to
consuming nothing, sugar reduces hunger.
But you don't need to take my word for
it. They show data that we'll go get
into as well. First, what effect did
these three drinks have on the
hypothalamus? Here we have images from a
connectivity analysis. That means that
we're looking at imaging of the
hypothalamus and the connections
displayed in color to other regions of
the brain. So if there's more yellow and
red, there's a greater connectivity in
that region. Then we see the three
comparisons. So sucralose, our
non-nutritive sweetener compared against
sucrose sugar. Then the same sucralose
versus water and then sucrose sugar
versus water. Clearly there are
differences with sucralose compared
against other conditions.
What about the blood flow that we
discussed? Remember the relationship is
reduced blood flow in the hypothalamus
is related to reduced hunger. Looking at
that data, we see that the hypothalamic
response meaning increased blood flow on
the vertical axis. If it goes up, that
means more activity, more blood flow.
You can see the three conditions below.
The individual puncta are the results of
each participants and the black dot is
the average result. So comparing the
conditions, we see the sucralose leads
to greater hypothalamic blood flow
activity compared to sucrose or water.
I'd even argue that we should change how
that's described because it seems to me
that the sucralose condition maintains
activity while the other two reduce it
since the values for sucralose sit
around the zero or baseline mark there.
We'll look into further evidence of
that, but what we really need to know if
this leads to changes in actual hunger.
Before that, there's additional data on
the different effects that based on
people's body weight. And if you're
interested in full analyses across all
my work, consider joining the Physionic
Insiders. That includes live sessions
with me, cheeseburgers, lettuce, tomato
on wrong script. Sorry. Uh that was my
lunch order. It includes written
research reviews, simplified protocols
and guides, a once a month podcast that
covers everything that you need to know
and more. The link to join the insiders
is in the description box. I hope to see
you there. So, here are the data on
hunger along with more on the
hypothalamus activity and effects on
blood glucose sugar levels. The red
condition is the sucralose, blue is
sugar or sucrose and the green is water.
As seen although poorly in the previous
data, the hypothalamic response is more
so reduced in the water and sucrose
conditions than there's really an
increase in the sucralose condition. But
both do occur. As predicted, only the
sucrose condition showed an increase in
blood glucose over time, which speaking
to the time element, for some reason the
researchers used 1, two, and three as
markers of time, but those actually
correspond to 10 minutes postbaseline,
35 minutes post baseline, and 120
minutes post-baseline. Okay. Now,
hunger. Fascinatingly, the water and
sucralose conditions seem to follow a
similar hunger experience. They both
increase but not really differently from
one another which tells us a key piece
of information before that. The other
comparison sucrossse also shows an
increase in hunger over time but the
effect is blunted over time compared to
the other two conditions. So this tells
us that sucralose while it might create
differences in the activity of the brain
especially the hypothalamus and regions
therein there is no added hunger effect
compared to consuming water. A more
appropriate conclusion would be to say
that sucrose, so sugar, reduces hunger
slightly in a way that sucralose does
not. Then again, that isn't much of a
shock considering that sucrose also
elevates blood glucose levels and has
calories, all of which have separate
hunger reducing effects. If we zoom out,
however, the researchers point out that
there's mixed evidence on if sucralose
and non-nutritive sweeteners as a whole
affect weight, which would be a telltale
sign of overeating. Some associative
studies indicate that there is a
correlation between increased
non-nutritive sweetener consumption and
increased body weight, but most
randomized control trials indicate
either a neutral or opposite effect. So,
greater consumption leads to reduced
body weight. So, this can get pretty
confusing. As it stands, the stronger
evidence suggests that non-nutritive
sweeteners do not lead to weight gain.
I'd also add that uh although sucralose
did show changes in the brain that are
not seen with sucrose or even water, the
hunger effects were in line with water
consumption and the effects relative to
sucrose were mild. And in the grand
scheme of an entire diet, I have my
doubts this would actually make a huge
difference, especially since there isn't
an additive hunger effect, just a lack
of hunger repression. So, in short, yes,
sucralose leads to changes in the brain,
but no, it doesn't lead to an
unreasonable outsized increase in hunger
when compared against a proper control
in this study. Everyone is different,
but these data on average do not
indicate a strong reason to reduce
sucralose consumption. Look, I like you.
I might even like like you. So, would
you I don't
know. Want to go on a date with me to
the next video?